Welcome, everyone, to fall
quarter and welcome to CS329A.
I hope you made it
to the right class.
This class is on
self-improving AI agents.
Anyone made it to
the right class here?
Yes.
Yes?
OK.
How many of you are here and
doing masters at Stanford?
OK.
PhD?
Few of you.
And then undergrad?
OK.
So masters is the
big crowd here.
There's a good balance.
It's a really good balance.
So we'll introduce ourselves.
So I'm Akansha.
I have been working in large
language models for a while,
and I'm an adjunct
professor at Stanford.
And I'm also in research at a
startup called Reflection AI.
Hi, I'm Azalia Mirhoseini I'm.
An assistant professor
in the CS Department.
And Akanksha and
I met each other
when we were at Google Brain.
Google Brain.
Yeah, back in the day.
And then Google DeepMind.
And I also worked on Claude
and Anthropic and Gemini
at Google DeepMind.
And we are so excited to
teach this course again.
This is the second
time we're teaching.
Of course, we have
made some updates,
both to the lectures
and also the way
we are conducting
everything for the course.
And we were just so amazed
by the amount of interest
for people to join this course.
So we are excited
to have you here.
The course website is
at cs239a.stanford.edu.
We have updated the website
in terms of all the lecture
materials and the papers
that you'll be reading,
as well as what's
the homework schedule
to expect the project proposal
and project structures as well.
So in today's
lecture, we'll start
with an overview of
large language models,
just how the scaling trends
have evolved over the last five
years.
And then we'll
focus more on what
we will cover in this class.
And then from there, in the
second half of this lecture,
we'll cover the
course logistics.
And that part, you should
pay a lot of attention
to, because that
influences your grades.
So let's take a look at
an overview of the trends
for large language models.
So one of the aspects
that has been mind blowing
since GPT 3 came out
is that as you scale up
the number of parameters in
a model, they get better.
And what this means is that
language models like Bert and T5
were good.
But as we increase the
number of parameters,
they got really better.
They perform much better.
And what this led to is
something called a scaling
loss for large
language models, which
are used in building
the base model for--
the pre-trained base model.
And as you increase
the amount of compute--
so there are three graphs here.
As you increase the amount
of compute on the x-axis,
the loss function on
the y-axis goes down.
And the more compute
you have put in,
the more the test
loss goes down,
which leads to a better model.
So that was one big
aspect that led to GPT 3,
then all the subsequent--
ChatGPT, PaLM,
Gemini, and so on.
And then similarly,
as you increase
the data set size on
x-axis, the test loss
goes down further on the y-axis.
So that's another aspect of--
another axis of scaling that
leads to better language models.
And the third one is, of
course parameter counts.
So if you increase the number
of layers in a transformer
or the amount of parameters that
are there in the language model,
that improves the
loss value, and that
leads to a better model.
And this has been the
foundation for a lot of-- this
has been the foundation
for a long time,
until last year, where
this was starting
to hit some kind of
a saturation point.
So from 2018 to almost 2024--
this graph is a
little bit outdated.
But from 2018 to 2024,
as the model size
has gone up almost
consistently, we
have been increasing
the size of the model.
So you started with
something like Bert
was 340 million parameters, GPT
2 was 1.5 billion parameters,
and then GPT 3 was 175
billion parameters,
and then PaLM was 540 billion.
And then there was a bunch
of subsequent models.
And GPT 4 is estimated
to be there, which
is trillions of parameters.
So you can imagine
that there has
been an exponential
growth in just the model
size for large language models.
The large stands for that
they're growing in size.
And that has been one of the key
areas in which the models have
been getting better.
So why do we care about
the models getting bigger?
What does this lead to?
So as I was explaining that
as the models get bigger,
they continuously improve in
performance on natural language
benchmarks on various
other benchmarks, reasoning
benchmarks, and so on.
And then the other
interesting aspect
that I will show
you in a moment is
that they learn how to
do few shot learning.
So earlier, you
have to fine tune
the model for specific domain.
But just by giving
a few examples,
the model can follow
that template and reason
in that same vein,
which makes it extremely
easy to prototype things.
And then the third aspect
is that as the models become
bigger, they have
emergent behavior where
the capabilities like reasoning
only emerge in larger models.
So just to understand few shot
learning or zero shot learning
here.
So if the model is given
a question or a task,
like translate English to
French, it's able to give--
so this is called a prompt.
Like it's a given a task,
translate English to French.
And then it's asked
to translate cheese
to whatever is the French word.
If the model can predict the
answer without actually being
trained on the specific
task, then that
would be called
zero shot learning.
And then few shot
learning, in addition to
giving the description
of the task,
you're also giving
a few examples.
So in this particular
case, it's giving,
translate English to French.
And it's given a few
examples of the translation
from English to French.
And then it's asked
to translate cheese
and it's able to translate that.
And you can see that
this capability shows up
in the large language models
across a large number of tasks.
And that has been
one of the key areas
that GPT 3, PaLM, and
other models enabled.
And then that
subsequent innovations
came from reasoning
aspects of this.
So on the reasoning side, as
models have become bigger,
they have this emergent
behavior of reasoning,
which Azalia will tell us
a little bit more about.
So as the models
become bigger, not only
we have this
predictive scaling laws
property that we know how
the loss function is going
to go down as we throw
in more compute data
and parameters in
the model, there
are new behaviors that
appear in the model
that they didn't have before.
And we never could predict that
until we had these bigger models
and saw this behavior in them.
And one of the most important--
one of those behaviors is the
chain of thought behavior.
And for those of you who
are not familiar with this,
here is how it works.
So in a usual
prompting of a model,
we can ask a model, in
this case, a math problem.
And then we can give
it a one shot example.
Here is a math problem,
here is the answer.
Now I ask you a similar but not
exactly the same math problem.
And the model is
expected to answer that.
And the model might be able
to use the one shot example,
or it might not be.
But we can do better here
by not only give an example,
but also provide the reasoning
or the chain of thought
on how we got to that answer.
So in this case, the question
is a very simple question.
Roger has five tennis balls.
He buys two more
cans of tennis balls.
Each can has three tennis balls.
How many total tennis
balls does he have now?
And instead of just
saying 11, you're
walking the model through
how to get to this.
Roger started with five balls.
Two cans of three tennis balls
is 6, and 5 plus 6 is 11.
And with this example,
then the model
has become familiar with the
process to get to the answer.
And it can leverage that
to answer new problems.
Well, obviously, this is
a very simple problem.
Any 1B parameter model
nowadays can solve this.
Doesn't need an example or a
few shot or a chain of thought.
But the chain of
thought property
itself is a property that
is holding to this day.
And it's a very, very
important property
for the reasoning models
and all the thinking models
and much of the progress that
we have seen in the past year
or so.
Now, this property
again appears as we
have larger and larger models.
Here are three models,
LaMDA, GPT, and PaLM.
And as you can see,
the chain of thought.
And this is some results
on some math data set.
And these models,
when they're smaller,
like eight billion parameter
for LaMDA, or for GPT,
around 7 billion,
they can't really
benefit from chain of thought.
It doesn't do anything for them.
But as they become larger
or for a pull mother
again at 8 billion, it can
leverage this chain of thought
property and learn from the
reasoning and the process that
is provided in the context in
order to solve problems better.
And not only that, there
are other abilities
to solve new tasks as we
increase the size of the models.
Like, for examples,
models can all of a sudden
solve mod arithmetics better or
solve word unscrambled problem
just by having this larger
size and this property.
You see that all of a sudden,
it appears at a certain size.
And because of all
of this, we still,
as in frontier
companies and labs,
are still interested in
pushing the scaling laws
and not only get the
natural kind of progression,
but also we will
see more and more
of these emergent behavior that
is going to be very important.
Now, a little bit
of history here.
So ChatGPT was launched
in November 2022.
Obviously, it was one of the
most successful apps or software
ever created.
The time to reach one
million users for it
was five days, which is
significantly faster than many
of the other famous software
that you can see there,
or services that
you can see there.
And there were
pieces of innovation
on top of just scaling up the
parameter size of the model that
were very important to
make ChatGPT what it was
and to make that leapfrog
over the previous models,
like GPT-3, so on.
And two important pieces here
were the instruction tooling
and the reinforcement learning
from human feedback, which
we are going to briefly
mention in the next slides.
But throughout
this course, we are
going to learn more
and more about them.
And then we're going
to learn about all
of these in more details.
But let's just take a step back
and see how the process works.
So the pre-training
step is the step
at the beginning of any
language model training.
That's the easiest step.
And we just train the model
to predict the next token out
of all sorts of text
and data, and so on.
And then this is
the fine tuning step
that was a key differentiating
factor for a model like ChatGPT.
And let's start with
the first aspect
of fine tuning,
which is alignment
with human preferences.
So when a model is
pre-trained, it has no sense.
It has seen all data on
the internet, in the books,
everywhere.
But it has no sense of what is
right and wrong and what is.
It just statistically knows
about the state of the worl,
but does it doesn't
exactly know things or know
how to follow instructions.
So the next step in
training these models
is the step where we
try to steer the AI
models to follow the goals
and preferences and values
of humans.
And this is still a big problem.
It's a big issue.
We haven't mastered it yet.
But as we progress,
models are becoming
better and much more powerful
in the things that they can do.
So it turns out that we can fine
tune the models to be aligned.
For example, here are
some graphs that show,
what if we take our base model
that's just pre-trained and fine
tune it for things like
sensibleness or safety?
And these are data
that we have collected.
These are high quality
data for showing the model
what we mean by what's safe and
what's unsafe or what's sensible
and what doesn't make sense.
And these are more curated,
more highly curated data
that we pass to the
model for fine tuning
and to make the
model more aligned
with the values or the
preferences of humans.
So going back, let's just walk
through this process again.
So the first stop when we take
a pre-trained language model
is fine tuning with next
token prediction, which
follows the same
process as pre-training.
But this time on data that
is much more higher quality.
For example, this could be data
from books, creative essays.
Data that companies
pay a whole lot,
millions of dollars or
hundreds of millions
of dollars potentially,
to buy this data that's
really high quality.
And then we train them.
We fine tune the model
on those, and the model
becomes much better
as a result of that.
The next step is
instruction tuning.
And by instruction
tuning, what we mean
is that we show the model.
Again, traditionally
in the past two years,
this instruction tuning
data is a combination
of human generated
data role templates
and the synthetic data.
But the way this instruction
fine tuning works
is that we do have instruction
and then question answer pairs,
where the model learns how
to follow the questions
and answers them.
For example, here, an
instruction tuning data set
could be about the weather.
Please answer the
following question,
what is the boiling
point of nitrogen?
And then this is the answer.
Or we can have chain of
thought fine tuning, where
we show the model how it
can walk through a process
to get to the answer.
And then we have the label.
We have the result over here.
And this is like these pairs
of questions and instructions
and answers.
And again, this
data set is very--
there's a lot of effort that
goes into this data set.
And the quality of data set
and the generality of it
has a lot of impact on
the quality of the model
that we get at this stage.
And after this
point, then the model
becomes more and more like
the models we see today.
You can ask them questions, you
can go back and forth with them.
They have this sense of
how to perceive a question
and how to walk through some
process to get to an answer.
And the next step after
instruction fine tuning
is this process of using
human preferences and fine
tuning the model based on that.
And this process is called
RLHF, or Reinforcement
Learning from Human Feedback.
The way this is different
from the previous step
is the way we create
the objective function
and create the data.
So in this case, instead of just
creating some supervised prompt
and labels, we are basically
creating a reward model
out of human preferences.
So companies spend a lot of
money asking humans, sometimes
experts, sometimes just humans,
normal humans, about questions
and the answers
generated by the model.
And we asked the
humans to rate them,
to see which one is correct,
and which one is not correct,
and that's how we can create
some sort of a reward model
here.
And this reward model
is instead of human.
Then we can use the
reward model in order
to guide the
parameters of our LLM
towards generating
answers that are
in line with this reward model.
So basically we
want the generations
by the model to be such that
this reward model says yes,
these are good generations.
We're going to learn
more about this here,
but we wanted you to
have the high level
idea of what RLHF means.
We can have different
reward types,
different types of reward.
For example, we
could ask the model
to reward a pair
of answers based
on their correctness or
helpfulness or specificity
or harmlessness.
All reward functions
that we can define.
And depending on how we
want the models to be
and what we care most about, we
can weigh these different reward
models and use that
in the RLHF process.
So these step at a
high level, of course,
there's a lot of
effort goes into that.
But pre-training and then fine
tuning on higher quality data
instruction tuning and RLHF
were the core components
that made up a model like
ChatGPT over something that
existed, over all the
large models like GPT-3
and prior models.
So that made a huge difference
in how good and capable
the models were.
So that was very cool
up until last year.
Or a year and a half ago.
Pre-training and then fine
tuning were the big pieces.
But since a year
and a half ago, it
turns out inference is
also a frontier for making
the models much more capable.
So and that opened a
whole set of whole lot
of new research and
directions and ways
that we can make
the model better.
So let's talk about
it a little bit.
Like this is the work we
did in my lab last year.
Last summer, and it was
called Large Language Monkeys.
And it's inspired by the
infinite monkey theorem.
And it's related to
inference scaling.
How many of you have heard of
the infinite monkey theorem?
OK, that's a good amount.
So the idea of the infinite
monkey theorem, what it says
is that it's not proven.
But what it says is that if
you have a monkey and a typing
machine, and then we keep
letting the monkey type all day
forever, after
some time, we will
have the works of William
Shakespeare in the things
that the monkey types.
So we were inspired by
that to name our project.
But the idea here
was that, let's have
the LLM be the monkey.
And let's ask the model
over and over again
to solve a given input problem.
You can think of it as parallel
sampling or parallel generation.
So instead of asking the model
once to solve the input problem,
you can ask it many times.
And also, let's assume you
have some sort of verifier
or selection mechanism so you
can pick which one of these
generated responses
were correct.
And then you output
that in your system.
That becomes the final output.
So the model, instead of
generating one answer,
generates many, many answers.
And then your verifier
selects which one of them
is correct and then outputs
one of the correct ones.
You can think of a verifier
as, say, some unit tests.
If the problem is
generating code,
the verifier could
be the unit test
that we run against
the code, and we
see which one of
the code generation
passes all the unit
tests, and so on.
The reason this can
be a possibility here
is that models are not--
there is some
variance in the way
the models generate responses.
It's not deterministic.
And you can even control the
variation in the model responses
with this thing
called temperature.
So you can force the model
or encourage the model
to generate more different
responses as you ask a question.
And here, now let's see some
of the results of this repeated
sampling.
For a bunch of tasks, like
math and coding benchmarks,
we increased the number of
samples per problem from 1,
which is the normal
one, to 10,000.
And here, we are showing
the coverage or the fraction
of problems that are solved by
at least one of these samples.
And what we are seeing here
is that so the red line,
the red dashed line,
was the GPT-4o model.
And while these blue and green
lines, which were the normal HP,
the normal 3HP and 7AB, were
worse than GPT-4o model with one
sample.
But if we increase the number
of samples from these models,
in all of these cases, they do
better than the GPT-4o model.
And what it says is that it kind
of seems like the models already
know a whole lot more than
what you get out of them when
you just ask them once, right.
So this is the underlying
property of inference scaling,
because it seems like we can
get a whole lot more capability
and problem solving
ability from these models
if we just bring in
this inference scaling.
Here, we are showing
repeated sampling,
but there are many
other ways to do that.
So the reason it's
called inference scaling
is that we are not touching any
of the parameters of the model.
The model is fixed, and we
are just at inference time.
We are creating different
ways to generate,
to produce generations
from the model
and use them to generate
higher quality answers
or answers to harder
problems for the model.
The interesting part here is
that for some of these problems,
out of these 10,000 solutions,
maybe three or four of them were
correct for a single problem.
So it shows that
how important it
is to scale the
inference to really get
to the core capability
of the models.
But what is the
difference of ways
of traversing all of the
possible answers and just
[INAUDIBLE]?
Sorry, what's the question?
What is the difference
of just ways
of traversing all the possible
answers and [INAUDIBLE]?
So the possible answers
need to be generated somehow
by the model, right?
So the space of all possible
answers to the model
is way bigger.
if we do like a tree
search or a random search,
it's way bigger, right.
There's no way to hit.
Even imagine we are asking a
human, just sit down and solve
this problem, right.
Of course, there's no
limit to human creativity,
human's creativity.
But there is a limit to how many
generations we can have, right.
Or if we randomize
things, there's
a whole lot set of answers
that can be generated.
And this is highly
sample efficient, right.
10,000 is not a whole lot.
Especially like, for
example, for the math f to f.
Some of these problems are
really hard IMO level problems.
These are really hard problems
that a tiny model like a 7
and Llama ATP can solve.
I was thinking, how
does the latency compare
to when you do actually generate
all those samples compared
to the GPT-4o, right?
How does the latency--
is tradeoff for you?
Yeah, of course,
there's a tradeoff.
And we touch on
that in the lecture
that I go more
details towards this.
The parallel samples,
the good thing about them
that they can be
run in parallel.
So from a latency perspective,
that's less of an issue.
But of course, there
is the frontier
of cost tradeoffs between how
much compute you're spending.
And we will look into that.
And it varies.
It varies depending on
the type of and complexity
of the problems.
Yes?
This approach where you have
a verifiable domain like math
and coding and how do you
handle it when you don't have--
Yes, great question again.
When you have verifiers,
it's much easier.
When you don't have
verifiers, there's
this whole set of
research on how
to train LLM as Judge or
LLMs reward functions or LLMs
with tools becoming.
And we're going to
learn about that all.
We have a lecture just
dedicated to verifiers, so.
Yeah?
Just a quick question, sorry.
So does this generalize to
any positive temperature?
So as the limit, as the
temperature goes to infinity--
No.
Yeah, we can have the
temperature being too high,
because it's going
to be gibberish.
The model doesn't generate.
So there's actually
a research project
last year was on tuning that or
figuring out what temperature.
Usually if you go beyond 1.2
or so, it's not great, yeah.
Yeah.
But there are other
tricks that you can
do to make the model be more--
have more diversity in
the type of answers.
And that can be useful.
All right.
So let's look at this.
So now, again, going back to
the events of last year, year
and a half, we had
the DeepSeek model.
I think it came out in December.
Christmas.
DeepSeek came out December 2024.
Oh, wow.
It's been a short time.
Short time or long
time, I don't know.
So then models like
DeepSeek came last year.
So basically, a core
innovation in DeepSeek.
And then the one series Gemini
thinking and such were that.
Now we are bringing this fine
tuning and test time scaling
together.
Because with this test
time scaling and the models
themselves, we have
this new engine
that we can generate a
whole lot of synthetic data.
For example, for problems
like for math problems,
where we know the answer.
We can have the model generate
different answers that leads
to that final golden answer.
Or for the coding problems,
we can use the model
to generate tons of data
during test time scaling, tons
of quality data to
solve coding problems.
And that becomes part
of our training set.
Now we can use that to fine
tune the model to become better.
So that, bringing
these two together
became a big piece in thinking
models and reasoning models.
And this is an area that is
really, really important.
There's just so much
to be explored in this.
Because again, it's
open-ended, right.
There's no boundary in how good
the models can become with test
time scaling, and then
bringing that back
to the process of training the
model or fine tuning the model
to become better
is very exciting.
And that's the
self-improving piece
that we are very excited about.
So a little bit about
reasoning models.
In the language monkeys, what we
were showing was the coverage.
If we had access
to verifiers, we
can see the log linear scaling
laws with the number of samples.
And OpenAI, when they
released o1 last September,
they showed the log
linear relationship,
this time with pass at one for
these hard aiming benchmark,
which is a set of really
difficult math questions.
So what they're showing
here is that as they're
increasing test time
compute, and this
is in log scale, the
accuracy, the past one
accuracy of the model goes up.
And this is for test time alone.
Previously, this has
been shown for training,
but it's very interesting
that this kind of scaling
applies to test time as well,
without changing the parameter
count of the model.
I'm going to walk you
through a few examples of how
this reasoning or test
time scaling works
with models like O3 or Gemini.
So one motivation here is that
for difficult problems, just
like humans, think a lot
more, spend a lot more time,
or consider many
different strategies,
thinking models do the same.
And they may use a chain of
thought or other techniques
to just go about
solving a problem.
And there are different
steps to that.
For example, problem
analysis is one step.
The model first sees a problem
and tries to analyze it.
Then it can do the
task decomposition.
Breaking a task into simpler
tasks that are more addressable.
Then there is the self-evolution
strategies where the model tries
something, sees the feedback.
For example, runs some
tests on the code or uses
a calculator, or just
judges the answer.
And it can use that
feedback to optimize itself.
There's self-correction, and
there are alternative proposals.
If something doesn't
work, the model
can backtrack and try
a different approach.
These are some key principles
that the model probably
at some point, pieces
of it were trained
as part of the training data
set were curated by humans.
But a big part of it is also
the model acquiring these skills
during this fine
tuning process and RL
from synthetic data process
that the model does.
Here is an example of
how o1 does analysis.
The model is asked to write a
bash script that takes a matrix
and then outputs the
transpose of that matrix.
And the model starts
with, just like humans,
starts thinking, what are the
pieces, important pieces, here?
So the user is
requesting a bash script.
Let's understand the input and
output formats of this matrix,
and so on.
So the model just thinks itself.
And amazingly, it's like a
progression of chain of thought.
This is like helping the
model finding the answer.
But the difference between
chain of thought and this
is that the model itself is
producing this chain of thought.
There's, of course, task
decomposition, in this case,
for the approach.
The model thinks about
parsing the input,
building the matrix as an
array of arrays and so on.
There's also self-correction,
which is a big important piece
of--
this is an important piece here.
And I don't know
how many of you have
seen that when trying
with the models
that you can see
the thinking traces.
And this is actually
pretty common.
The models start something, and
then in the middle says, wait,
the correct--
there's something wrong, maybe.
And maybe I need to fix that.
And it's very, very cool that
the model can do that itself.
So reasoning models, when they
came out, like models like o1,
compared to a model like GPT-4o,
which wasn't a reasoning model,
they tend to be better in
obviously the reasoning task.
For example, in math
calculation, data analysis,
programming and such,
they all outperform
GPT-4o, but not necessarily
in personal writing or editing
texts, and so on.
Yeah, question?
Do you think the
gains due to this
asking for a reasonable
price is due to actually
the act of generating
this reasoning traits,
or just the act of asking
the model to think or do
these decomposition at all?
Like, for example, if you
said, think step by step,
but don't generate
out loud, but actually
generate false positive
[INAUDIBLE] without saying.
Yeah.
I repeat the question.
You were saying, do you
think the reasoning models
are becoming what they are?
Is it based on the
loud way of thinking?
I think the question is that,
is it because of the reasoning,
or is it because of things step
by step, the chain of thought?
Is it the data that's
making a difference,
or is it the instruction?
I mean, so the data basically
has made the model become
a generalized thinker, right.
And all of these steps,
breaking down a problem,
being able to backtrack,
being able to do analysis,
all of these are these
skills that the model
has learned during this thinking
optimization process that
now generalize to other things.
And they're helping
the model right now.
So I think the other
way to look at it
is as Azalia presented,
repeated sampling.
So if you had just a base
model right after pre-training,
it would be able to
do some reasonings.
But at the same time, it
will generate different kinds
of reasoning chains.
And it doesn't quite know
which one is correct.
So a lot of what we
will cover in train time
or test time scaling
really comes down
to it learns, which is correct.
So pass it, one
accuracy goes up,
which is what you were seeing
in the reasoning models.
As opposed to pass
it k or coverage,
which is what you were seeing in
the repeated sampling results.
Yeah.
And one other way to think about
it, yes, these deep thinking
and things that
the model generates
is actually helping
the model every time
to solve a new problem.
And although it's very
expensive for the model
to generate those things, still,
we want them to generate those,
because it leads
to better answers.
Any other questions?
Yes?
Can you use a different
model for the reasoning step
versus generating
the final answer?
Maybe a smaller
or a purpose built
one just in case the final
answer is a large problem?
So typically, the
reasoning capabilities
have gone up with
the model size.
So if anything, you would use
the larger reasoning traces.
And then maybe you collect
a bunch of reasoning traces
and then have a smaller
model summarize the answer.
So the models, this is at least
currently, things may change,
they like their own traces more.
Even if the traces are
coming from a better model,
they tend to their traces, their
own generated traces, more.
And we're going to
have talk about Swirl.
This is one of the papers that--
The multi-step reasoning.
The multi-step reasoning
that we talk about,
what if we bring
a different model
not in the context of
generating reasoning traces,
but in the context of
evaluating and giving feedback?
And we're going to
see that as well.
But models, surprisingly
or not surprisingly,
they like their own
traces a lot more.
For reasoning models, how
are they taught to reason?
Is it a hard coded
set of sequences
that are taught to do
traces, or are they
somehow fine tuned
to say, we need
to do this much or
this kind of thing,
which will cause the
traces to generate?
So I don't think there's a
published piece of work that
really covers this bit.
It's both, yeah.
But it's a bit of both.
And at the same
time, the base model
did have the thinking
capability to begin with, right.
Go do some amount of thinking.
One thing that we will
cover in the class
is this notion of outcome
rewards model and process reward
model, and how you can use that
feedback to get the model back.
Yeah, there's always
some bootstrapping.
Like, OK, here are
different ways.
Chain of thought
itself, which is heavily
used in the instruction
tuning of data set,
shows the model some
ways of how to think.
And there could be
some templates showing
for the model, fine tuning.
But the things that the model,
if you just ask it any question
and it comes up
with that, there's
a whole lot of
generalization that.
So models have gone
way above like what
the data or instructions that
are used for training them.
Yes?
In sampling, is there a way
to make the number of samples
from--
Please speak up.
The number of
samples, can they be
dependent on problem difficulty?
I don't think there's a
published piece of work that
does that.
So there is follow
up work to that
where we use a reward model,
and then you can use that.
So assuming the reward model
has some notion of complexity.
If you haven't
solved, it can guide
more sampling, or whether
it's repeated or parallel.
But that's definitely
an interesting direction
to explore.
Yeah.
OK, we need to get to
the-- oh, we haven't--
yeah, let me cover this.
OK, so you now know about
large language models.
And then you heard about how
they learned how to think,
and then they learned
how to reason.
So what's next, and why
is this course relevant?
So a lot of what
this course is about
is that large language models,
as chatbots or as reasoning
models, are basically
still single turn or just
in the chat format.
So they're not accomplishing
a task for you.
They're fun to interact with,
but they're not necessarily
accomplishing a task for you.
What has happened this year
almost in the last few months,
and it's been surprising,
is that agents
like Cloud Code or Deep Research
have really enabled people
to do real world workflows.
So they're agentic
workflows which
can achieve tasks that you
ask them to do end to end.
So, for example, if you want
to go research and figure out,
where should I rent a home
perhaps for the entire year,
if I want to take a
class at Stanford,
the model would actually be able
to do a whole bunch of analysis
and go look at a lot
of different websites
and actually
summarize the results
and give you pros and
cons of different places.
This used to not
be possible before.
So this will cover a little bit
of how that becomes possible
and how this course allows
you to learn about that.
And then Cloud Code for
example, if any of you
are Codex, which is the
coding agent from OpenAI,
if you're using
that, what you'll see
is that just by giving
instructions in English,
you can modify files, or you
can figure out test cases
and whatnot.
So it really has become a
coding productivity tool
in the day-to-day workflows
for software engineers
at this point in time.
So what is the transition
from LLM to agents?
So as I was giving you the
example of deep research
and of coding agents,
basically now, the model
can be given a goal.
And it will plan out the
steps that it will go interact
with the environment.
And based on the feedback, it
will correct its steps until it
achieves the goals or it
will come back and say,
I cannot achieve the goal.
So this notion of having
some notion of a goal,
taking actions towards that
goal, getting the feedback,
and then deciding
when to stop, that's
what makes agents different
from the chatbot types of what
we were doing before.
And this also might
require interacting
with tools which are external to
what the model itself is doing,
getting some inputs from there.
But it still stays on
track of whatever task
it's choosing to
accomplish, which
might mean that it has to
have some form of memory
to keep track of the tasks
that it's trying to accomplish.
So what has been accomplished?
So in several cases,
in simpler cases,
you can achieve these
end to end goals.
Deep research can be
accomplished end to end.
But in most scenarios,
you are still having
very static workflows.
So today, what exists is closer
to agentic workflows, where
you have some sort
of an input where
you're giving a model the goal.
And then what this
slide is showing you
is that one model
is perhaps giving
the output like a solution,
and then another model
is judging it and
then deciding based
on that, whether the
solution should be accepted.
So that's one orchestration
framework that's possible.
Deep research would be more
of the second one, where
you basically generating--
you're calling the LLM on
multiple possible inputs
and then aggregating
the things to get
the output, which will be a
summary of the deep research
results.
So this is a very
cartoonish abstraction
of what agentic workflows
might look like.
And you can
generalize from there.
But instead of having
very open ended loop
that I was showing
you here, where you're
supposed to go take an
action from the environment
and come back and
do some feedback,
it's easier for
open ended problems
to construct this graph by
hand of how a human would
do it and then get this feedback
perhaps from an LLM, which
is the LLM evaluator here.
So a lot of the
real world workflows
still have this paradigm.
But in certain cases, we are
starting to see signs of life
for what's possible
in this slide.
And coding being one and
research being another one.
So typically, the workflows
will have things like LLM calls.
So you would
basically call an LLM
with an instruction
or some form of input.
And then you're asking the
LLM to give you an output.
It will have some
form of verifiers.
We'll cover verifiers in
a whole lecture by itself.
It will have some form of
critics or judges, which
is effectively LLM
as a judge paradigm.
There might be tool calls.
For example, for
deep research, you
have to actually
go search the web
to figure out what
exactly is the content
that you should be looking at.
So there might be tool
calls of that form
or getting some value around
what exactly is the weather.
And similarly, search
would be another tool call.
And then you would
orchestrate these
in some form of a workflow.
So a simplest workflow here
would be prompt chaining.
So similar to reasoning models
where the task gets decomposed
into subtasks, prompt
chaining would simply
be like you have chained a
bunch of different subtasks
that you're supposed
to go accomplish
to achieve the end to end goal.
There might be routing.
Routing works for complex
tasks where you say, OK,
if this is very complex, then
go do this more complicated set
of LLM calls.
And it's less complicated
than do this simpler workflow.
There might be parallelization
where deep research is
one example where you can
have multiple LLM calls work
simultaneously on researching
different keywords
that you give as
input to the LLM.
And then finally, you
aggregate the output.
Or you might break the task
into independent subtasks
and then combine the solution.
Or you might have this
notion of orchestrator,
where you basically
are actually using
some sort of a, in simple
words, LLM manager.
So a central LLM is
actually doing the planning.
So in Cloud Code, you
actually start to see that,
that there is some notion of
a plan that it comes up with.
And then based on that plan, it
will make subsequent LLM calls.
You might have an
evaluator or a judge.
So instead of getting
feedback from real world,
like user or from some sort of
a actual running a unit test,
it actually might just
use LLM as a judge.
And we will have some homeworks
that will cover this aspect.
And then you might
have verifiers.
Verifiers are things where you
can actually verify the output.
So in code, for example,
if you run the code,
how do you know that
this code is correct?
So typically, as software
developers we write unit tests.
So similarly, verifiers might be
running some kind of unit test
to check, whether what
LLM generated is correct.
And in domains which are
verifiable, math, code,
and other domains that
are more rule based,
this verification is a
good way to give feedback
back to the model so that
it can correct its steps.
So most of these workflows
mean that the LLM
needs to be better at planning.
It needs to be better
at multi-step reasoning,
and it needs to be better
at self-improvement.
Like when it makes
mistakes, it needs
to be able to correct itself.
So effectively, these
are new paradigms
that the current set of
LLMs just with reasoning
were not quite accomplishing.
And these are some of
the topics we do plan
to cover in subsequent lectures.
And just to drive the point
home around coding agents.
So this is a very
simple example.
I should have updated
the slide for Cloud Code.
But basically what
this is showing
is that you have an
LLM agent and it's
interacting with the computer.
These days just
with the terminal,
you give it an instruction
where you might tell it that you
want to implement a test.
And then it has some
navigation of repositories,
searching of files,
all of these tool
calls around viewing
files, editing lines.
And then it will
go execute a bunch
of commands in the terminal.
And based on the output,
it might be like,
OK, I need to go
edit this other file,
or I need to go look
at this other file.
So if you look at this
loop, this very much
mirrors what was-- so this was
not quite reliable last year.
And it's just starting
to get reliable in what
we are seeing in the realm
of coding agents now.
Yes?
Can I ask why do you
think it's not reliable?
The general architecture
is, I would say,
not changed that much.
I mean, I think the paradigm
is very much the same.
It's mostly a matter of more
powerful models and then
better RL.
RL with verifiable
rewards is working.
The train time scaling
is working well.
I see.
How did you [INAUDIBLE]?
I mean, computer data, right.
One of those two.
But just also, once the
models start to get better,
there's this self-improvement
loop that kicks in.
Because you can now generate
tests, and the tests
become more reliable.
So in the published
pieces of work,
if you look at,
say, code monkeys,
which we covered
last year, if you
can generate unit
tests for whatever code
the model generated and then see
if the generated unit tests are
making things better, then
that's a very good way
to verify things, right?
Yeah, model based.
It seems like to some extent,
if we have good verifiers,
we can make the model
generate the right code.
But the question is,
how do we do that?
And there are ways to do it.
And we would be
happy for you guys
to take research projects
in that domain, too.
But obviously, it's an
active research area.
But there are ways to
make improvements that--
I think what you're alluding
to is this notion of generator
verifier gaps.
So it's easy for
models to generate
a whole bunch of nonsense or
sensible set of reasoning traces
or useful set of content.
But at the end of the day,
whether that's useful or not,
we need feedback loop for that.
And if you're creative writing,
how much feedback can you get?
So human feedback ends
up becoming a bottleneck.
In domains where you
can have good feedback,
that's where it's possible to
continue to improve the model.
And that but we're getting
robust verification,
a lot of robust
verification is hard.
So Azalia will cover a paper
that she did in her lab
about how to combine verifiers.
But verification
continues to be one
of the bottlenecks in this
space to make them better.
Yes?
Intuitively, I
think free training,
you get ability to survive
at such a large corpus.
So just to me, intuitively,
I'm trying to figure out
why there's such a big jump.
Because we're providing
a reward signal,
and we're trying to
elicit activities
that shouldn't
exist in training.
So I guess I'm just not--
I think this is still an
active area of research.
So there are different set
of opinions around what
really improves the model.
Is it RL, or is it
the pre-training,
the diverse data by itself?
And I don't think there is
a single point of consensus.
At this point in time,
both processes help.
What you just said, which I
will repeat for the class,
is that if pre-training
is the place where
the model, after
repeated sampling,
should be able to at least have
one solution correct out of
if it was generating a
large number of samples,
then this notion
of giving feedback
should improve the
passive one accuracy,
but should not
improve the model.
Why is it such a big jump?
But I think that whole loop is
not completely well understood.
It's like the
first signs of life
and it starts to
get commercialized.
But I think there's a
lot more research still
open in this area.
Yeah, that's right.
So that's only one way
of thinking about it.
There are at least
some signs of life
which say that you
can continue to do RL,
and that will continue
to improve the model.
Yeah.
OK.
So this is basically covering a
lot of the same set of points.
But one abstraction
that is worth
taking away from
this particular chart
is that even when you
give the model a goal,
it has to clarify
the user intent.
So it's not always obvious to
it what the model user wants.
And then it might go
search for relevant files.
And then whatever a set of
actions which chooses to take,
oftentimes, it needs some
form of verification.
In this particular case, it's
based on passing the test.
And it might actually generate
the test that it needs to pass,
which is also mentioned here.
But the key idea is that
if you give it a task,
how does it come
back, and how do you
know that it's going to
complete what you asked it for?
Oftentimes, the users will not
specify the problem well enough.
So clarifying the
user intent so that it
knows what to go look
for and how to verify
starts to become important.
And in models like
O3, I think they
have seen a lot of
these traces end to end.
So they are able to do the
planning, the reasoning,
the multi-step reasoning, and
come back with the conclusion.
But a lot of this is needed
for completing tasks end to end
or having an end to end goal.
And where this has
been super useful
is if you have repetitive tasks
like code migrations or version
upgrades, or if you need to
restructure the code base.
Or if you have tasks that
involve data engineering,
where you have to basically do
some sort of extract the data
and then do some sort
of cleanup on the data.
Or if you have to do some sort
of data warehouse migration.
So a lot of this work tends
to be extremely repetitive.
And it's much easier to just
delegate it to coding agents.
Same for unit tasks.
Oftentimes much easier to start
to give it to coding agents.
Another area where agents have
become extremely prevalent
is in customer support.
It's one of the
most thankless jobs
that when you are on the
customer support side of things
have to do, and using LLMs to
do that definitely streamlines
the experience in
interesting ways.
So one simple set
of examples ends up
being like you can use them
to do live transcription.
So that gives you
a very nice record.
And you're seeing that even
for meetings these days.
Another simple example is that
you can have Knowledge Assist.
So if you have a
database of information,
the customer support agent does
not need to know everything.
They can consult with
the LLM and get an answer
and surface the
relevant article, which
is better than having just
search, an index and search
by itself.
Smart reply.
So in chat, oftentimes, this
has existed for a while,
but you can use an agent
to give chat responses.
And then having a call
summary can help you--
you can use the call summary
to really improve the customer
experience by itself as well.
So overall, I think in
the customer support area,
there's multiple companies
that are going after this area.
But there are different
segments of the problem that
can be addressed using LLMs,
and they have been super useful.
And then there's also
the end to end stuff
that's starting to happen here.
And then the third
example that we will use
and actually some
of the homeworks
is that if you have
very complex topics
and you want to provide
a comprehensive report,
earlier, it used to be that you
had to do a literature review,
and then you had to
summarize each paper,
synthesize these things.
And these days, you can
just give it to an LLM
and actually do it for you.
In the study, maybe more
articles than you would.
So typically, if you give
it an example like, say,
2022 Winter Olympics
opening ceremony,
it will identify what
references to go look at.
Then it will construct an
outline of, OK, these references
are relevant or not.
And then summarize
each of the references
as to what is the
relevant content,
and then combine them to
create a full length article.
Which is very impressive
in certain cases,
and you'll get to try it
in one of the homeworks.
And then even more
forward looking.
These research
agents are starting
to be used as AI scientists.
So basically, they're starting
to assist scientists in, say,
solving math problems or
solving science problems.
So here, the LLM is used
as a brainstorming thing
to come up with ideas.
So the idea generation phase,
then the experiment iteration
phase, it might actually help
you iterate on the experiments
that you are hoping to work on.
This is from the
AI scientist paper.
And then in the
paper writeup phase,
it will help you improve
the paper writer by itself.
And what's interesting is
that even though these models
hallucinate just the notion
that they can come up
with so many different set
of ideas, as an AI scientist,
it might actually
brainstorm or give you
ideas outside what you would
have thought if you had just
taken a bunch of courses
or if you're a researcher
and you've been in the
field for a long time.
Sometimes reading the
web allows these alarms
to come up with ideas that
are way outside the box
and can be a very good
brainstorming way.
So these have been super
useful in the AI scientist
style of work.
OK, so let's move
to course logistics.
But before that, do
we have any questions?
Yes?
I just want to clarify.
So is reasoning and chain of
thought linked in training,
or is it just a
prompt engineering
that was accidentally
discovering
these kind of capabilities
in larger models?
And if so, are there other
emergent behaviors, sites,
or reasoning that you
think might be discovered?
So I mean, it was not
baked in by design.
It was basically discovered.
I mean, we gave
it hard problems,
and then we saw that
it was basically--
by having reasoning chains,
it was doing better.
So the GSM 8-K was the first
paper that showed signs of life
of this.
And then with larger
model like PaLM,
we actually saw that
this was a very big deal.
In one of the examples there
was that it could explain jokes,
which was very impressive.
And then from there, the
reasoning models have emerged.
But it has read all of the
web, so it has definitely
seen data, which is more
methodical and systematic.
But the reasoning
models are trained to be
reasoning more and more, right.
The entire reasoning is
not an emergent behavior.
The reasoning models, they're
trained to be thinking.
But the models are converging.
So the models are going to be
trained such that they know when
they need a lot of reasoning
and when they don't.
And to generate the answers.
But chain of thought originally
was an emergent behavior.
They noticed that, oh,
if we explain things,
a model gets better.
Are there any emergent
behaviors in larger models?
I don't think I would see it
as emergent behaviors per se.
But I think as I was
mentioning, we usually
go looking for
certain things, right.
So in the agentic workflows,
what we're looking for
is planning, which is
a form of reasoning.
We're looking for
multi-step reasoning, which
we will cover in class as well.
And then we're looking
for self-improvement
or self-correction.
So all of these capabilities
would be nice to have.
And what gets the models
there is a set of questions
that are worth--
there are papers on
this kind of thing.
Like self-correction,
backtracking, things like that.
It's like yes, you
could call it emergent,
but you could also
say, think about it,
that they have seen
this kind of behavior.
And it's like it's reinforced in
the way that they're fine tuned.
So yeah, it's hard to say.
OK, so let's go through the
logistics for the class.
Here's a list of all
the amazing topics
that you're going
to learn about.
Yeah.
This is very cool.
I think the main
thing to remember here
is that the overall
theme stays the same.
And then we'll also have
guest lectures around
from folks in frontier AI labs
and covering things all the way
from say, how has post
training evolved, or even
multimodal agents in robotics.
So it's going to be a mix of
lectures and guest lectures.
And of course, your
project presentations.
So here is some logistics
that you all know.
The prereq are there.
Just make sure that you are
comfortable with these prereqs
as you register in the class.
So we have the external website.
But make sure that
you check Canvas.
That's where we send out the
latest updates at all times.
And we try to
upload the lectures
before we start in every
class, so you have access
to the lectures.
And we already have the due
dates for all the assignments
and all the projects.
So you can check it out.
So this quarter, we are going
to have three homeworks.
That's a difference
from between this class,
and that's one of
the differences.
So we have one more homework for
you all that we have designed.
And the TAs have
done a great job.
And that helps you hopefully
learn these topics better
and more in depth.
And then we also have
a course project.
So the course project is where
you can unleash your creativity
and your way of building
agentic systems or going deeper
into a question and designing
experiments around it and see
what works and what doesn't.
We will provide some
examples or suggestions,
but it could be completely on
you how to design this project.
You will have some
examples from last year,
like the successful projects
from last year as well.
It's going to be
uploaded to Canvas or--
Actually, we'll display
them on the website.
Oh, on the website.
Oh, cool.
The public website, so
you can also see that.
So yeah.
So for the course project, I
think the main thing to remember
is that we will
have API credits,
and you can work in teams
of two to four people.
Right?
Yeah.
Or up to four, I guess.
Up to four?
OK.
You can be one if
you really want that.
We suggest you team
up with others.
At the very least,
you have more credit
collectively so you can
run more experiments.
But then you might also
find a friend collaborator
along the way, and you
can do something bigger.
And we are going to have this--
what is this?
The course project.
Yeah, we're going
to let you know
about some of the previous
years and some ideas
that you can take.
Here are some course project
examples that are acceptable.
For example, a new evaluation
data set or a new benchmark.
You can design a project
around the reliability
of an agentic system
that already exists.
You can take a
benchmark that exists
and try to hill climb on
it with whatever idea,
great idea that you have.
And then or you
can just-- we are
going to have a whole lot of
papers covered in this course.
And we are showing
all of that to you.
They're all on the website.
So as we give these
lectures, we expect
you to also have
read those papers
or read the papers along
the way and develop
better and deeper intuitions
on how these methods work.
And your project could always be
improving those or questioning
one of the decisions
that they have made
and trying to change
that or evaluate that.
Negative examples are
like a survey paper.
We want something
researchy here.
So we just don't want just
an app that you put together
and you just show us something.
It has to be like,
here is the hypothesis.
Here is the question
that we wanted to answer.
Here is the type of
improvement we wanted to see
or the type of properties
we wanted to analyze.
And then we have built that.
Right, we want something that--
something more than
white coding, basically.
In terms of milestones,
I think it's
worthwhile to remember that
you want to start early.
So you need to have a project
proposal somewhere around--
I think we put it early October.
And then--
It's on the website, yeah.
It's on the website.
And then for the midterm
project presentation,
we do want you to
have some progress.
So two weeks after
the project proposal,
we do expect you to have--
so start thinking about what
experiments you want to run by
the time you get to the project
proposal so that you actually
go run them for the midterm
projects.
So we do expect you to have made
some progress in the midterm
project presentation.
It should not just be,
here is a proposal.
And then the final report
has a lot of weight.
And then the final
poster presentation
will be the end of the quarter.
Yes.
Let's see if we
do a [INAUDIBLE].
I think so.
If you add to it, right.
[INAUDIBLE] is
independent study, right?
Yeah, independent research.
Yeah, yeah, that's fine.
I think--
I mean, as long as
you're doing actual work
and it's not just like reusing
the work from an exact copy
of something, yeah.
We had students publishing
papers out of their projects
in the last quarter.
So in the last time
we taught the class.
So that's something we could
be one of you or many of you
this time, again, turning
your research project,
working more on it,
and then turning it
into a publication
at conferences.
And so here is a save the date
for our poster presentation.
It's going to be December
12, 4:00 to 6:00 PM.
So we would want you to be
there and present the posters.
We'll have people
from industry joining.
That's where you can brag
about what you've done
and just meet new people.
Here is the course
grading rubric.
So we have three homeworks.
That's 50% of your entire grade.
And then another 50%
is on the project.
And the duration of
these are aligned
with how much the grading is
allocated to each of these.
And we, of course, expect
you to honor the honor code.
And let's see, office hours
will be posted on Canvas.
You can ask your questions.
We really, really encourage
you to ask questions on Edson
and make it public.
Probably if you have
a question, it's
very likely others
have the same question.
So please help us do
broadcast this to everybody.
Edson is, again, you
can ask questions,
and then Gradescope is where you
submit your project milestones
and everything else.
Yeah, the homeworks
and everything.
We have the
following late policy
that we think is
within the generous--
on the generous side of things.
And because the class
is big this quarter,
we really can't
make any exceptions.
So try to use these
late days wisely.
Audits are not allowed, but
we will have the course--
we will have the videos--
Videos on YouTube, eventually.
Eventually.
And that's it.
Any questions?
No?
All right.
OK.
Thanks, everyone.